Records of the Human Resources Development and Operations Policy Vice Presidency
World Bank Group Archives
Records of the Human Resources Development and Operations Policy Vice Presidency
1993 - 1995
WB IBRD/IDA WB_IBRD/IDA_91
30.24 linear feet of textual records; 1 VHS tape
World Bank Group Archives
Human Resources Development and Operations Policy Vice Presidency
The Human Resources Development and Operations Policy Vice Presidency (HRO) was one of three Vice Presidencies created during President Lewis Preston's reorganization of January 1, 1993. Following the abolishment of all Senior Vice Presidencies on December 1, 1991, Preston initiated a larger reorganization in 1993 that aligned the Bank's organization with the priority areas of its poverty reduction effort. The result was three new thematic vice presidencies: the HRO; Finance and Private Sector Development (FPD); and Environmentally Sustainable Development (ESD).
The vice presidencies were responsible for:
* Providing operational support to the Regions through participation in Sector Operations Division (SOD) task teams, undertaking specialized assignments for the Regions, providing ad hoc advice, distilling lessons of operational experience and disseminating best practices, and definition of sector and operational policies
* Assisting in identifying and addressing the Bank's skisurells mix and training needs; * Providing information and intellectual support to interested actors outside the Bank
* Liaising with the UN and other official and private organizations
* Delivering complete products to the country directors in the 'clustered subsectors', where the small number of expert staff can most efficiently be located in the central Vice Presidency.
As part of the 1993 reorganization, the former Population and Human Resources Department was terminated and its divisions were split between two newly created departments: the Population, Health and Nutrition Department (PHN) and the Education and Social Policy Department (ESP). Both of these departments were placed in the HRO Vice Presidency along with an Operations Policy Department (OPR). The OPR absorbed the functions of: the former Central Operations Department (COD); the International Economic Relations Division (OPRIE); and the UN Office in New York (OPRNY) transferred from the External Relations Department (EXT).
In January 1994, President Lewis Preston created a secretariat within the HRO (HROAN) responsible for managing a program of the Bank's 50th anniversary activities.
On July 1 1995, HRO became Human Capital Development and Operations Policy (HCO). At this time education, health, nutrition and population functions were again combined in a single department named the Human Development Department (HDD). A Poverty and Social Policy Department (PSP) was also formed and placed in HCO.
Published
The majority of the records in this fonds are chronological files created by the HROVP. Most of the contents of these files are correspondence to and from institutions, agencies, governments, and departments external and internal to the Bank. The fonds also includes records which relate to communications as well as governance-related activities of the HROVP.
The Education and Social Policy Department (ESP), Poverty and Social Policy Department (PSP), and Poverty, Gender, and Public Sector Management Department (PGP) records sub-fonds contains the records created during the existence of those departments between the years 1993 and 1997. These departments combined a number of sector teams or groups, including Gender and Development, Poverty Analysis and Policy, and, temporarily, Education within the Human Resources Development and Operations Policy Vice Presidency (HRO). Individual staff often supported more than one sector at a time and this is reflected by folders that contain records of more than one sector. As a result, the records of these departments have been placed in the HRO fonds rather than separated and dispersed into their respective sector fonds.
Records were initially transferred from HROVP to the Bank's Institutional Information Services Center (IISC) prior to their transfer to the Bank's Archives.
Accruals are not expected.
Records were initially transferred from HROVP to the Bank's Institutional Information Services Center (IISC) prior to their transfer to the Bank's Archives.
* For records created by the HRO's sector departments and their predecessors and successors, see Records of the Population, Health, and Nutrition Sector ([WB IBRD/IDA WB_IBRD/IDA 89](https://archivesholdings.worldbank.org/records-of-population-health-and-nutrition-sector)).
* See Records of the Education Sector ([WB IBRD/IDA WB_IBRD/IDA_88](https://archivesholdings.worldbank.org/records-of-education-sector)).
* See Records of the Sector Policy and Research Vice Presidency (PREVP) and the Sector and Operations Policy Vice Presidency (OSPVP) ([WB IBRD/IDA WB_IBRD/IDA_93](https://archivesholdings.worldbank.org/records-of-sector-policy-and-research-vice-presidency-prevp-and-sector-and-operations-policy-vice-presidency-ospvp)).
* See Records of the Human Development Network (HDN) ([WB-IBRD/IDA-HDR](https://archivesholdings.worldbank.org/records-of-human-development-network)).
* See the Records of the Poverty Analysis and Policy Sector ([WB IBRD/IDA WB_IBRD/IDA_98](https://archivesholdings.worldbank.org/records-of-poverty-analysis-and-policy-sector)).
Records are subject to the World Bank Policy on Access to Information.
- Chronological files, 1994 - 1995; WB IBRD/IDA WB_IBRD/IDA_91-01; 2.40 linear feet of textual records
  Published
  Series consists of chronological files created primarily by the HROVP. Records date from February 1994, to December 1995; records from July to December 1995 are from the Human Development Department (HDD). The majority of the records found in these files are correspondence. Correspondence to and from external agencies, institutions, and governments generally relates to information exchange, collaborations on projects and research, and conference attendance. Correspondence to and from other departments and vice presidencies in the World Bank is also included. This relates to information exchange, collaborations on projects and research, and conference attendance as well as to HRO's contributions to Country Assistance Strategy reports and participation in meetings. Records also include back-to-office reports, discussion of HRO human resource issues, and comments on HRO staff reports and programs. Records related to the Bank's 50th anniversary activities are also included; these records were created or receivedby the secretariat established in the HRO (HROAN) responsible for anniversary activity's coordination.
  The order of the files as it existed upon transfer from the IISC has been maintained. Files are arranged chronologically.
  Accruals are not expected.
  * See Records of Population, Health and Nutrition Sector - Chronological files ([WB IBRD/IDA WB_IBRD/IDA_89-01](https://archivesholdings.worldbank.org/chronological-files-11)) of HRO subordinate units during the same time period.
  * See Records of Education Sector - Director and Front Office records ([WB IBRD/IDA WB_IBRD/IDA_88-01](https://archivesholdings.worldbank.org/chronological-file-of-elizabeth-king)) for chronological correspondence of units reporting to HRO.
  Records are subject to the World Bank Policy on Access to Information.
  - Human Resources Development [HRO] - General File - 1994 Chronological File - Volume 7, 1994-11-01 - 1994-12-30; 01337909
  - Human Resources Development [HRO] - General File - 1994 Chronological File - Volume 6, 1994-09-01 - 1995-03-12; 01337908
  - Human Resources Development [HRO] - General File - 1994 Chronological File - Volume 4, 1994-05-11 - 1994-06-29; 01337906
  - Human Resources Development [HRO] - General File - 1994 Chronological File - Volume 3, 1994-05-01 - 1994-05-31; 01337905
  - Human Resources Development [HRO] - General File - 1994 Chronological File - Volume 1, 1994-02-14 - 1994-03-31; 01337903
  - Human Resources Development [HRO] - General File - 1995 Chronological File - Volume 6, 1995-10-02 - 1995-10-31; 01337974
  - Human Resources Development [HRO] - General File - 1995 Chronological File - Volume 4, 1995-07-05 - 1995-08-31; 01337972
  - Human Resources Development [HRO] - General File - 1995 Chronological File - Volume 3, 1995-05-01 - 1995-07-31; 01337912
  - Human Resources Development [HRO] - General File - 1995 Chronological File - Volume 1, 1995-01-09 - 1995-02-28; 01337910
  - Human Resources Development [HRO] - General File - 1994 Chronological File - Volume 5, 1994-07-01 - 1994-08-31; 01337907
  - Human Resources Development [HRO] - General File - 1994 Chronological File - Volume 2, 1994-04-01 - 1994-04-29; 01337904
  - Human Resources Development [HRO] - General File - 1995 Chronological File - Volume 7, 1995-11-01 - 1995-12-26; 01337975
  - Human Resources Development [HRO] - General File - 1995 Chronological File - Volume 5, 1995-09-01 - 1995-09-29; 01337973
  - Human Resources Development [HRO] - General File - 1995 Chronological File - Volume 2, 1995-03-02 - 1995-04-28; 01337911
- Communications, 1993; WB IBRD/IDA WB_IBRD/IDA_91-02; 0.09 linear feet of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to the dissemination of reports authored by the staff of HRO and its departments. Series also includes records relating to a seminar on Gender and Development organized by HRO.
  - Human Resources Development [HRO] - Operations Policy [VP] - Dissemination and Training File - Dissemination - Publications - 1993 Correspondence - Volume 1, 1993-04-27; 01218143
  - Dissemination and Training - Conference and Workshop - General - 1993 - Chronological Record - Volume 1, 1993-07-13; 01203478
  - Dissemination and Training - Publications - General - 1993 - Chronological Record - Volume 1, 1993-04-16 - 1993-06-03; 01203426
  - Human Resources Development [HRO] - Operations Policy [VP] - Dissemination and Training File - Dissemination - Publications - 1993 Reports, 1993-04-01 - 1993-06-01; 01218144
- Management and oversight, 1993; WB IBRD/IDA WB_IBRD/IDA_91-03; 0.03 linear feet of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to activities of the HROVP including staffing, policy development, and resource distribution.
  - Human Resources Development [HRO] - Operations Policy [VP] - Policy Development and Research File - General - 1993 Correspondence - Volume 1, 1993-07-20; 01203482
  - Human Resources Development [HRO] - Operations Policy [VP] - Administration File - Budget - General - 1993 Correspondence - Volume 1, 1993-02-23 - 1993-06-22; 01203481
  - Human Resources Development [HRO] - Operations Policy [VP] - General File - General - 1993 Correspondence - Volume 1, 1993-02-19 - 1993-05-11; 01203427
- Records of ESP, PSP, and PGP, January 1991 - May 1997; WB IBRD/IDA WB_IBRD/IDA_91-04; 27.72 linear feet of textual records; 1 VHS tape; Education and Social Policy Department (ESP), Poverty and Social Policy Department (PSP), and Poverty, Gender, and Public Sector Management Department (PGP)
  Between the years 1993 and 1997, the Education and Social Policy Department (ESP), Poverty and Social Policy Department (PSP), and Poverty, Gender, and Public Sector Management Department (PGP) were responsible for the functions of a number of different social- and poverty-focused sectors, including gender and development, poverty analysis and policy, and, temporarily, education. While the departments were organized into 'teams' or 'groups', activities often overlapped.
  ESP was created as part of the Bank-wide 1993 reorganization. The Population and Human Resources Department (PHR) was terminated and its functions were split between two newly created departments: the Population, Health and Nutrition Department (PHN) and ESP. Both of these departments were placed in the Human Resources Development and Operations Policy Vice Presidency (HRO). ESP absorbed the functions of the following PHR divisions: Education and Employment Division (PHREE); the Women in Development Division (PHRWD); and the Poverty Analysisand Policy Division (PHRPA). ESP performed operational and analytical work in four main thematic areas:
  * poverty analysis and social policy
  * labor markets and safety nets
  * women in development; and
  * education and training.
  The ESP Department was responsible for:
  * formulating and disseminating policies and guidelines for its sectors
  * monitoring the effectiveness of policies and approaches
  * identifying and disseminating best practices and lessons of experience
  * liaising with external organizations and professionals in the field
  * assessing skills requirements and upgrading skills; and
  * providing operational support to the Regions.
  On July 1, 1995, HRO became the Human Capital Development and Operations Policy Vice Presidency (HCO), and ESP was terminated. The education team of ESP was moved into the newly established Human Development Department (HDD) of HCO. The remaining teams were moved into the new Poverty and Social Policy Department (PSP). PSP contained four groups:
  * Gender Analysis and Policy
  * Poverty and Social Assistance
  * Labor Markets, Social Protection, and Public Sector Management
  * Participation and Non-Governmental Organizations.
  On December 31, 1995, HCO was terminated, and replaced by the Human Capital Development Vice-Presidency (HCD). PSP remained in HCD.
  As part of a Bank-wide reorganization in 1997, PSP sectors and functions were mapped into a new network-based structure. This process began in September of 1996 with a series of temporary relocations of PSP sectors. Labor Market and Social Protection activities were transferred to the Human Development Department (HDD) and then subsequently mapped into the new Human Development Network (HDN). The Participation and Non-Governmental Organizations team was transferred to the Environmental Social Policy and Resettlement Division (ENVSP) of the Environmentally Sustainable Development Vice Presidency (ESDVP). ENVSP was subsequently mapped into the Environmentally and Socially Sustainable Development Network (ESSD). In December 1996, the Human Capital Development Vice-Presidency (HCD) was terminated. The remaining PSP Groups of HCD were temporarily transferred to the Development Economics Vice Presidency (DEC) under the oversight of International Economic Department Director (IECDR) Masood Ahmed. While being overseen by DEC, the Gender Analysis and Policy Group, the Poverty and Social Assistance Group, and activities related to Public Sector Management temporarily became the Poverty, Gender, and Public Sector Management Department (PGP). The transition was finally completed in July 1997 when the sectors within PGP were individually mapped into the new Poverty Reduction and Economic Management Network (PREM).
  This sub-fonds consists of records from the Education and Social Policy Department (ESP) and its successors the Poverty and Social Policy Department (PSP) and the Poverty, Gender, and Public Sector Management Department (PGP). Records include chronological files created by ESP, PSP, and PGP. Records related to the Annual Progress Report on Poverty (APPR) and the ESP/PSP Discussion Paper Series are also included. The sub-fonds additionally includes subject and activity files maintained for PSP/PGP Director Ishrat Husain. The sub-fonds also includes PSP briefing letters prepared for World Bank senior officials and records related to conferences, seminars, symposiums, workshops, and meetings organized and attended by PSP staff.
  A portion of the records were initially transferred from HROVP to the Bank's Institutional Information Services Center (IISC) prior to their transfer to the Bank's Archives. A transfer of PSP records was transferred from PSP to the Archives at the inception of the PREM Network with no approved records retention disposition schedules. Additional records were transferred to the Archives from the PREM Network in September 1997 using approved records retention and disposition schedules.
  * See Records of the Office of the Chief Economist -- Records of the Office of the Vice President, Development Economics and Chief Economist and later Senior Vice President, Development Economics and Chief Economist (DECVP) -- Subject Files of Masood Ahmed, Director, International Economics Department (IEC) Concerning the Development of the Poverty Reduction and Economic Management Network (PREM), ([WB IBRD/IDA DEC-03-85](https://archivesholdings.worldbank.org/subject-files-of-masood-ahmed-director-international-economics-department-iec-concerning-development-of-poverty-reduction-and-economic-management-network-prem)) for records related to the mapping of PSP and PGP units into PREM.
  *See the Records of the Poverty Reduction and Economic Management Network ([WB IBRD/IDA PREM](https://archivesholdings.worldbank.org/records-of-poverty-reduction-and-economic-management-network)) for PREM Vice President sector department oversight and support records related to the PGP units mapped into PREM.
  *See the Records of the Education Sector ([WB IBRD/IDA WB_IBRD/IDA_88](https://archivesholdings.worldbank.org/records-of-education-sector)) for additional records related to the Education Sector.
  *See the Gender and Development Sector ([WB IBRD/IDA WB_IBRD/IDA_97](https://archivesholdings.worldbank.org/records-of-gender-and-development-sector)) for additional records related to the Gender and Development Sector.
  *See the Records of the Poverty Analysis and Policy Sector ([WB IBRD/IDA WB_IBRD/IDA_98](https://archivesholdings.worldbank.org/records-of-poverty-analysis-and-policy-sector)).
  - PSP/PGP Director's subject and activity files, January 1992 – May 1997 (predominant July 1995 to December 1996); WB IBRD/IDA WB_IBRD/IDA_91-04-04; 16.38 linear feet of textual records; 1 VHS tape
    This series consists of the subject and activity files of Poverty and Social Policy Department (PSP) and Poverty, Gender, and Public Sector Management Department (PGP) Director Ishrat Husain. The records in this series were used as reference for Husain as well as support for the activities of PSP and PGP sector teams and groups. Records include: memoranda; correspondence; agenda; meeting minutes; working papers; and policy paper drafts for numerous working groups, task forces, and policy development committees focused on a particular topic or project.
    The series additionally consists of PSP budget records consisting of: correspondence; memoranda; Draft Discussion Notes from Human Capital Development and Operations Policy Vice Presidency (HCO); and PSP business work plans for fiscal years 1997 to 1999. Additional records include correspondence and memoranda related to the mapping of PSP/PGP Groups into the HDN, ESSD, and PREM Networks. Other planning records include: PSP Week correspondence from May 1996; "Next Step Action Program" correspondence and memoranda from fiscal years 1996 to 1999; and correspondence, memoranda, reports, and handbooks related to designing performance and poverty monitoring indicators for PSP and World Bank operations poverty reduction monitoring efforts from 1993 to 1996.
    The series also includes records related to PSP's predecessor Education and Social Policy Department (ESP) inherited by PSP/PGP Director Ishrat Husain. This includes correspondence and memoranda related to ESP's planning and compliance to poverty reduction policies outlined in IDA 9 and IDA 10 Agreements dated 1992 and 1993. Additional correspondence and memoranda address the following topics: performance indicators; subnational indicators; and social funds. It also includes records related to the "Program of Targeted Interventions (PTI)" pursued by ESP in 1993. Records detailing procedures of ESP and Human Resources Development and Operations Policy Vice Presidency (HRO) are also included for the years 1992 to 1995, but some PSP correspondences are interfiled after 1996. A speech transcript file consisting of speeches given by ESP and PSP staff, the HROVP, other World Bank unit staff and officials, and Ishrat Husain are also included for the years 1992 to 1996.
    Arranged by subject.
    A folder-level list for this series is available in electronic form.
    - China: CEM, 2020 - 1v, 1995-12-01 - 1996-12-31; 01458339
    - Best Practice Papers - 1v, 1996-04-01 - 1996-07-31; 01458338
    - Civil Society - 1v, 1995-08-01 - 1996-12-31; 01458341
    - Civil Service Paper - 1v, 1995-12-06 - ?; 01458340
    - CSIS ( Center for Strategic and International Studies ) Poverty Studies - 1v, 1996-01-01 - 1996-10-01; 01458342
    - Gender ( Member of Committee on Gender Issues ) - 2v, 1995-10-01 - 1996-12-01; 01458344
    - Development Grant Fund ( DGF ) - 1v, 1996-10-01 - 1997-05-31; 01458343
    - Labor Market Study - 1v, 1996-05-01 - 1996-10-01; 01458346
    - Governance - 1v, 1995-08-01 - 1997-03-31; 01458345
    - NGOs ( Non Governmental Organizations ) - 2v, 1995-07-01 - 1997-01-31; 01458348
    - Mali Pilot Participation Project - 1v, 1995-11-01 - 1996-05-31; 01458347
    - World Bank Non-Governmental Organization [NGO] Committee - General Correspondence, 1995-02-20 - 1997-05-18; 01458349
    - Project Watch List / Project Alert - 1v, 1995-10-01 - 1997-03-31; 01458350
    - Participation Action Plan - 1v, 1995-07-01 - 1996-08-31; 01458351
    - Participation: Flagship Operations and Miscellaneous - 2v, 1995-10-01 - 1997-05-31; 01458352
    - Participatory Poverty Assessment ( PPA ) - 1v, 1995-12-01 - 1996-12-31; 01458354
    - Participation: Sourcebook / Public Sector Agencies - 1v, 1995-12-01 - 1996-05-01; 01458353
    - Post Conflict Reconstruction and Failed States - 2v, 1995-03-01 - 1996-05-31; 01458355
    - Poverty Monitoring - 1v, 1995-12-01 - 1996-10-31; 01458357
    - Poverty Progress Report - 1v, 1996-02-01 - 1996-08-31; 01458358
    - Public Expenditure Paper - 1v, 1996-01-01 - 1996-03-31; 01458359
    - Post-Conflict Reconstruction and Failed States - 2v, 1995-12-01 - 1997-05-01; 01458356
    - Quality Assurance Group - 1v, 1997-04-01 - 1997-05-31; 01458361
    - Severance Pay - 1v, 1995-07-01 - 1996-07-31; 01458362
    - Social Investment Funds - 2v, 1996-05-01 - 1997-05-31; 01458363
    - Social Policy - 1v, 1993-07-01 - 1996-01-31; 01458364
    - Social Sector Secal - Russia / Ukraine - 1v, 1995-12-01 - 1996-10-01; 01458365
    - SPA Working Group - 1v, 1994-10-01 - 1996-03-02; 01458366
    - Special Grants and Trust Funds - 1v, 1995-10-01 - 1997-01-31; 01458367
    - Public Sector Management ( PSM ) - 1v, 1996-05-01 - 1996-12-31; 01458360
    - Structural Adjustment - 1v, 1995-07-01 - 1996-10-31; 01458368
    - Task Force on Poverty in Sub-Saharan Africa - 1v, 1995-08-01 - 1997-03-03; 01458369
    - The 20 / 20 Initiative - 1v, 1995-12-01 - 1996-12-31; 01458370
    - Social Strategy Task Force - 1v, 1996-03-01 - ?; 01458372
    - United Nations ACC Task Forces - 1v, 1996-06-01 - 1996-10-31; 01458373
    - World Summit for Social Development - 5v, 1994-06-01 - 1995-03-31; 01458374
    - World Summit for Social Development - 4v, 1994-09-01 - 1995-05-31; 01458375
    - Uganda Case Study - 1v, 1997-03-01 - 1997-05-31; 01458371
    - World Summit for Social Development - 3v, 1993-03-01 - 1994-12-31; 01458376
    - World Summit for Social Development: Follow up - 1v, 1995-09-01 - 1996-05-01; 01458377
    - Social Capital: Integrating the Economist's and the Sociologist's Perspectives - 1v, 1996-11-01 - 1997-05-01; 01458385
    - Public Sector Management - 1v, 1996-06-01 - ?; 01458388
    - Social Strategy Task Force Retreat - 2v, 1996-03-01 - 1996-05-01; 01458387
    - Adapting Capacity Building Strategies to the Needs of War-Torn Societies - 1v, 1996-10-24 - ?; 01458390
    - Participation Sourcebook Launch - 1v, 1996-02-26 - ?; 01458391